hey push students let's cover everything
you need for period
[Music]
7 before we start print out the free
speed review sheet that goes along with
this video the link is in the
description below go ahead and look at
period 7 Circle any people events or
vocab things that you don't quite
remember that you know you need to focus
on when you study once you've mastered
those topics you can check them off and
move on to the next one all right here
we go Frederick Jackson Turner published
his Frontier Thesis after the 1890
census where he declared that the
American frontier was closed he also
argued that the American identity was
based on conquering these Western lands
now that there was no more Frontier in
the Continental us Americans began to
look outwards for raw materials and new
markets one of the first acts of
American imperialism was the Hawaiian
coup Americans living in Hawaii were
capitalizing off of the sugar trade so
they helped to overthrow the Hawaiian
Monarch so the US can Annex Hawaii in
addition to the lucrative sugar trade
Hawaii was also a strategic location in
the Pacific giving America's stepping
Zone to Asian markets two important
imperialists that you want to know are
Alfred Mahan and Jose jiah strong Mahan
an American naval officer argued that a
strong Navy was critical for America's
growth and power while strong was a
minister who believed it was the duty of
Americans to spread their culture and
religion throughout the world
imperialist ideals also led to the US
involvement in the Spanish American War
which demonstrated a significant change
in American foreign policy some
Americans felt compelled to support Cuba
in their independence from Spain these
feelings were heightened by yellow
journalists like William Randolph Hurst
and Joseph Pitzer tensions escalated
when reporters published a delone letter
where a Spanish Diplomat criticized and
insulted President McKinley a week later
the USS main sunk in Havana's Harbor the
Press published this as the work of
Spanish mindes leading Congress to
declare war the war ended with an
American victory the Treaty of Paris
granted America Cuba Guam in Puerto Rico
America also purchased the Philippines
and although the conflict with Spain
lasted just a few months the Philippine
American war carried on for years there
are several significant foreign policies
you definitely want to know for period
7even first is John Hayes open door
policy which gave America access to
foreign markets in China while also
keeping it out of European control next
was the Roosevelt cor which was an
expansion of the Monro Doctrine theer
Roosevelt argued that the US had a right
to intervene in Latin American Affairs
to protect their economic interests and
maintain stability in the region
president ta supported Dollar Diplomacy
which sought to secure order in Latin
America through economic means like
investment in loans and wood Wilson
implemented moral diplomacy which meant
the US would try to support governments
who emphasize democracy and free trade
at the turn of the century America
experienced a period of social economic
and political reform known as the
Progressive Era journalists called muck
Breakers use expose journalism to fight
corruption for example Lincoln stepin
wrote The Shame of the Cities to expose
political corruption and Ida Tarbell
wrote about Johnny rockefeller's
ruthless tactics while he was growing
his Standard Oil Company the most famous
was up in St Clair's The Jungle which
exposed the horrors of the meat packing
industry and led to the establishment of
the Food and Drug Act as well as the
Meat Inspection Act Teddy rosi's
presidency was focused on reform he
sought to break up bad trust and
monopolies and his Square Deal focused
on consumer protections controlling
corporations and conservation economic
reforms included the Clayton Antitrust
Act this strengthened the Sherman
Antitrust Act and limited the power of
monopolies and President Wilson signed
the 16th Amendment which instituted the
federal income tax and he created the
Federal Reserve political reform focused
on voting practices the 17th amendment
allowed for the direct election of
senators Americans also saw the
introduction of initiative referendum
recall and the secret ballot just like
they had in other periods women played a
major role in bringing about reforms
carry Nation for temperance which led to
the 18th Amendment Alice Paul in groups
like the national American women's
suffrage association contributed to the
passage of the 19th Amendment which
finally allowed women the right to vote
after World War I in 1914 the Great War
broke out in Europe but President Wilson
was determined to stay isolated and
declared neutrality however the American
economy benefited significantly selling
supplies especially to the Allied Powers
despite Wilson winning re-election in
1916 with the slogan he kept us out of
War America ultimately joined the war in
1917 after Germany continued using
unrestricted submarine warfare on
American Merchant vessels Americans also
felt threatened after the Zimmerman
Telegram was released in the Press while
young men were drafted or volunteered
with the American expeditionary forces
women and minorities stepped up at home
to keep the country running by filling
jobs in factories or on the farms and
just like in previous Wars American
Liberties were restricted during World
War I Congress passed the Espionage and
the Sedition Act towards the end of the
conflict Wilson crafted his 14 points in
hopes of preventing another Global
crisis however most of the points were
ignored in the Treaty of versailes
because Britain and France wanted to
punish Germany by forcing them to sign
the war guilt clause and pay heavy
reparations the only one of Wilson's 14
points that was incorporated was the
League of Nations and international
peacekeeping body this made the treaty
ratification process difficult for the
Senate reservationists like Henry cabat
Lodge disagreed with article X of the
treaty which required countries to join
the League of Nations they fear that
this would drag America into another
global conflict instead they favored a
return to isolationism at the turn of
the century we also saw a renewed push
for african- American Civil Rights in
1909 prominent leaders like web de booys
idb Wells and Thug Marshall formed the
NAACP to fight for equality Justice and
rights they also sought to tackle
disenfranchisement in the South Marcus
Garvey on the other hand supported black
nationalism economic self-sufficiency
and back to Africa movement around the
same time millions of African-Americans
left the oppressive Jim Crow South in
search of jobs and freedoms in the north
this became known as The Great Migration
and after World War I the growing number
of African-Americans in Northern cities
like Harlem led to the Harem Renaissance
artists like Langston Hughes shared the
oppression of the African-Americans
through poetry while musicians like
Louis Armstrong ushered in the Jazz Age
later leaders like a Philip Rand helped
fight for equality and Employment
Practices he threatened to March on
Washington DC to protest discrimination
and defense industry jobs as America
mobilized for World War II this forced
SDR to create the Fair Employment
Practices committee and inspired future
civil rights leaders like Martin Luther
King Jr and during World War II
African-Americans made significant
contributions both serving in the war
and working in Industries at home this
led to the double V campaign which
fought for victory abroad over fascism
and victory at home for equality after
World War I America entered a period
known as the raring 20s it was
characterized by rapid economic growth
and a culture of consumerism Americans
were eager to buy Goods that were scarce
during World War I as well as new
appliances and the radio but America
also entered into a Red Scare following
the Russian Revolution Americans were
afraid of Communists coming into the
country which increased nativism this
led to the quota acts which severely
limited immigration espe especially from
Southern and Eastern Europe prohibition
dominated the 1920s But ultimately it
was a failed social experiment that led
to the rise of organized crime the most
famous crime ring was Chicago's alcapone
American women celebrated their
contributions to World War I and the
passage of the 19th Amendment some
adopted the Flopper Style by cutting
their hair wearing short skirts and
smoking and drinking in public however
many also held on to the traditional
Victorian values and finally in 1925
John T Scopes was arrested for teaching
evolution in a Tennessee Public School
the Scopes Monkey Trial was a media
spectacle and it represented the ongoing
debate between modern values and
fundamentalist ideas this was a theme
that had dominated the decade much of
the economic growth of the 1920s was
through expansion of consumer credit and
unregulated banking practices while
consumers Ed credit cards to buy cars or
washing machines investors bought stock
on margin both factories and Farms
contributed to over production causing
prices to drop all of this played a role
in the stock market crash known as Black
Tuesday the official start of the Great
Depression and this coincided with the
Dust Bowl which forced Farmers to
migrate in of work President Hoover
continued the lair policies of previous
presidents because he thought the
economic crisis would fix itself however
after unemployment reached 25% and
homelessness continued to rise he
realized he needed to take action
despite creating the Reconstruction
Finance corpse to provide loans and
create jobs it was too late Franklin D
Roosevelt beat Hoover in a landside
election in 1932 FDR ran on his new deal
platform where he promised to provide
relief reform and recovery for the
American people upon taking office he
instituted the Fireside Chats where he
used the radio to connect with the
American public and help rebuild
confidence in the government after
announcing his bank holiday FDR's first
New Deal passed creating the
agricultural adjustment act and the
Federal Emergency Relief act all within
the first 100 days his second New Deal
followed which included further reforms
like the Social Security Act despite
creating millions of jobs and
instituting significant economic reform
many criticized FDR and his new deal
while huie long argued that the New Deal
did not do enough to help the poor in
working class Business Leaders argued
that the New Deal bordered on socialism
he was also criticized for trying to
pack the Supreme Court in an effort to
protect his legislation after several of
his New Deal programs were declared
unconstitutional but ultimately the
Great Depression didn't end until World
War II as tensions mounted in Europe
with the rise of fascism America passed
a series of Neutrality Acts but
gradually got more involved with the
Allied cause in 1939 FDR approved the
cash and carry program which was
followed by the Lend Lease Act in 1941
The Selective Service Act was also
passed which was America's first
peacetime draft ultimately the Japanese
attack on Pearl Harbor on on December
7th 1941 forced America to join the war
this caused an increase in anti-japanese
sentiments Executive Order 9066 forced
Japanese Americans living on the west
coast into internment camps for the
duration of the war This was later
upheld by the Supreme Court in the koram
Matsu case once America entered the war
many American minority groups supported
the effort over 1 million
African-Americans served in World War II
but all branches of the Armed Forces
remained segregated the Tusk Airmen
served as the first African-American
pilots in the armed forces about 45,000
Native Americans also enlisted in the
war both men and women the Navajo code
talkers in the Pacific and the comman in
Europe played a vital role in the
American war effort and for the first
time women were allowed to enlist in the
military in groups like The Women's Army
Corp they served in a variety of
non-combat positions like nurses
telephone operators truck drivers and
mechanics but on the home front once
again women filled the positions of the
men who had left from the war as seen
with Rosie the Riveter during the war
American troops helped the Allied Forces
defeat Hitler in Europe with leaders
like Dwight D Eisenhower who helped lead
the D-Day campaign at the same time the
island hopping campaign was used in the
Pacific to fight the Japanese at home
the office of scientific research and
development also worked on the top
secret Manhattan Project developing a
new technology the atomic bomb even
though Germany surrendered in May of
1945 Japanese forces continued to fight
President Truman who took over after
FDR's death would accept nothing but
unconditional surrender from Japan he
approved the use of the atomic bomb
after the bombings of Hiroshima and
Nagasaki Japan finally surrendered in
the fall of 1945 officially ending World
War II so what does this look like on
exam day for causation you will probably
be asked about the causes of imperialism
the causes of the Great Depression or
the effects of the new deal for
comparison you could be asked about
similarities and differences on the home
front between the first and second world
wars or you could be asked about the
difference in the fundamental values
versus modernism in the 1920s and for
continuity and change they'll likely ask
about changes in foreign policy so be
ready to talk about the inner War period
you could also be asked about changes
during the Progressive Era so be ready
to write about the progressive
amendments and economic reforms like the
Federal Reserve check out the aush
ultimate review packet for more help
we've got timeline study guides and
Essay practice follow the link in the
description below for a free preview and
if you think this video was helpful like
And subscribe thanks for
[Music]
watching